You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we get the low-
down on a bacteria
most people have
never heard of.
It’s called Helicobacter Pylori,
or H. pylori, for short.
And it can cause big
problems in your stomach.
For decades, Japan has had
the longest life expectancy
in the world, while spending
just a fraction on healthcare
compared to other
high-income countries.
This longevity has been attributed
in part to Japanese dietary patterns,
which are thought to have
contributed to their comparatively
low rates of coronary artery disease.
Japan has historically
had amongst the lowest rates
of colon cancer, breast cancer,
ovarian cancer, prostate cancer,
bladder and blood cancers.
Japan, however, has among the
highest rates of stomach cancer.
Yes, Japanese men may have had
seven times less prostate cancer
than Americans but got six
times more stomach cancer.
Is there some Achilles' heel
in the Japanese diet?
One of the first theories,
proposed in the 1970s,
was that it was the talc
used to polish white rice
to give it a glossy sheen.
That was the case with ovarian
cancer, which led to billions
in damages against Johnson
& Johnson's baby powder,
but that did not appear to be
the case with stomach cancer.
Is it just genetics? No.
Studies on Japanese migrants
show that as they and
their children Westernize
their diets and lifestyles,
their stomach cancer
rates drop accordingly.
Well, the most well-established
risk factor for stomach cancer
is H. pylori, a bacteria that infects
the lining of the stomach and
causes the chronic inflammation
that can lead to cancer.
H. pylori infection is considered
a Group 1 carcinogen, indicating
our highest level of certainty
that it indeed causes cancer.
Korea and Japan have the
highest rates of stomach cancer
and among the highest
incidence of H. pylori infection.
Case closed then, right?
The mystery seemed
to have been solved.
But then came the African enigma.
Countries such as Nigeria
had even more H. pylori,
but only a fraction of Japan's
stomach cancer rates.
Then came the Indian enigma.
H. pylori is twice as prevalent in
India than Japan, yet Indians get
ten times less stomach cancer.
Obviously, H. pylori alone
can't explain Japan's epidemic.
Though most cases
of stomach cancer
are thought caused by H. pylori,
most people with
H. pylori don't get cancer.
H. pylori is one of the most
common human infections.
It's been estimated that half
of the world's adult population
is infected with H. pylori, yet half
of us don't get stomach cancer.
There must be some kind of co-factor
in countries like Korea and Japan
that explains their
elevated cancer rates.
The inflammation caused by
H. pylori may just set the stage
for cancer formation,
increasing the susceptibility
of the stomach lining
to dietary carcinogens.
But what's so carcinogenic about
Korean and Japanese diets?
Studies that have compared
the dietary components
of different Asian populations
with similar H. pylori rates,
but dramatically different stomach
cancer rates, have suggested
preserved, salted foods—both fish
and vegetables—as the culprits.
Fresh vegetables and fruits, on
the other hand, were associated
with an 85% reduction in
stomach cancer odds,
whereas consumption of fresh
fish doesn't appear associated
with stomach cancer either way.
A review of 60 studies
found the consumption
of pickled foods was associated
with significantly higher rates
of stomach cancer, though
more so in Korea than Japan,
perhaps because per-capita
Korean consumption
of salt-fermented
vegetables like kimchi
is five to eight times greater.
You can't know for sure though
until you...put it to the test.
Pickled vegetable extracts can cause
DNA damage in cells in a petri dish,
but what about in people?
Researchers in Vancouver fed
people 30 ounces of fukujinzuke —
assorted vegetables
pickled in soy sauce —
or pickled cucumbers
over a three-day period.
Biopsies taken from their stomach
lining before the experiment started
were normal, as were
the biopsies taken after eating
fresh carrots or cucumbers.
But after just a few days of
consuming pickled vegetables,
moderate to severe tissue
abnormalities were found,
suggestive of stomach irritation.
The consumption of non-fermented
soy foods, such as tofu, edamame,
and soymilk is linked to a lower risk
of stomach cancer in Japan,
whereas no association was found
with fermented soy foods,
even highly salted miso.
The protection afforded
by soy foods was attributed
to the anti-inflammatory
and anti-oxidant effects
of the isoflavone
compounds in soybeans.
Salt itself isn't considered
a direct carcinogen, but it may
damage the stomach lining,
thin the protective mucus layer,
enhance H. pylori colonization,
enhance the penetration
of carcinogens, and enhance
the formation of carcinogens.
Even moderately high salt intake
is associated with significantly
increased risk of stomach cancer,
though in Japan this effect
may be limited to those
already suffering from
H. pylori-induced inflammation.
H. pylori is typically treated with
a cocktail of multiple antibiotics.
Is there any way to eradicate
it naturally through diet?
We'll find out next.
The salting and pickling of fish
produces a novel DNA mutating
chemical called CMBA, which is
formed from a reaction of the salt,
nitrite preservatives, and methionine,
an amino acid found concentrated
in animal proteins.
The nitrites can also interact
with other protein components
to form N-nitroso compounds,
a powerful class of carcinogens
found in cigarette smoke.
This may explain why processed
meats, such as bacon, ham, hot dogs,
lunch meat, sausage, have been tied
to increased stomach cancer risk,
but this extends to fresh,
unprocessed, unsalted meat as well.
But wait. I thought most stomach
cancer was caused by an infection
with a stomach bacteria
called H. pylori.
There's a synergistic interaction
between H. pylori-induced
inflammation gastritis and diet in
the formation of stomach cancer.
Check it out.
Researchers in China discovered
that even genetically
vulnerable individuals
infected with a particularly
pathogenic strain of
H. pylori did not appear to be
at increased risk of stomach cancer
unless they ate about an ounce
or more of pork per day.
An average pork chop
is like about six ounces.
This is a striking example of how
our diet can sometimes trump
both our genes and
environmental influences
like cancer-causing infection.
But is there a way to wipe out
the H. pylori in the first place?
Normally you'd use a triple
antibiotic cocktail of drugs
to kill off H. pylori, but patient
compliance is difficult to maintain
due to the quantity of drugs taken
and the adverse side effects.
Anything we can eat
to wipe them out instead?
Decades before the detoxifying and
anti-cancer abilities were discovered,
sulforaphane, that remarkable
compound in cruciferous vegetables,
was originally described
for its antimicrobial activity.
After hearing anecdotal reports of
individuals with H. pylori-induced
peptic ulcer disease
experiencing dramatic
and sometimes unexpected
relief after eating three-day-old
broccoli sprouts, researchers
at Johns Hopkins University
and elsewhere decided to put
broccoli sprouts to the test.
Not only did broccoli sprout extracts
kill antibiotic-resistant strains
of H. pylori in a petri dish,
some patients who
were given as little as
a third of a cup of broccoli
sprouts a day for a week
were able to eradicate
their H. pylori infection.
So how about a
randomized controlled trial:
broccoli sprouts vs. alfalfa sprouts?
And those given two to three servings
of broccoli a day worth of sprouts
were able to significantly cut down on
markers of both H. pylori colonization
and stomach lining inflammation.
Though broccoli sprouts may
be able to eradicate H. pylori
in the majority of patients, 56%,
the standard triple drug antibiotic
therapy is much more effective,
about 90% eradication.
Still, for those who don't meet
the criteria for drug treatment,
cruciferous vegetables may
present a safe, natural way
to combat H. pylori and the
development of stomach cancer.
A compilation of 22 population
studies found that eating more
cruciferous vegetables
was associated with
a significantly lower
stomach cancer risk, but
broccoli has never been directly
put to the test, but garlic has.
Observational studies dating back
to the 1960s on Japanese migrants
have suggested that allium
family vegetables—
garlic and onion family vegetables—
may be protective
against stomach cancer.
To date, there have been dozens
of such studies published,
and overall, eating lots of
allium vegetables was indeed
associated with significantly
lower stomach cancer risk.
There's evidence of publication bias
though, meaning there appears
to have been other studies that
maybe failed to show such an effect,
that were shelved
and never published.
Even if this weren't the case,
observational studies never prove
cause and effect.
Maybe low garlic and onion
consumption didn't contribute
to stomach cancer, for example,
but rather stomach cancer contributed
to low garlic and onion consumption.
Decades of H. pylori stomach
inflammation leading up to the cancer
may have led to individuals choosing
bland diets to avoid discomfort.
You can't know if garlic really
helps until you put it to the test.
Louis Pasteur was evidently
the first to describe
the antibacterial effect of
onion and garlic juices.
Petri dish studies have shown that
garlic is effective in suppressing
the growth of H. pylori at
concentrations achievable
in the stomach
with a single clove.
Even some antibiotic-resistant
strains are susceptible.
But does this translate into
stopping the growth of cancer?
A randomized, double-blind,
controlled trial was launched
to find out. Thousands
of individuals at high risk
for stomach cancer
from 13 villages in China
were randomized
into various combinations
of antibiotics, garlic supplements,
and antioxidant supplements.
And just few weeks of antibiotics
led to a significant decrease
in subsequent precancerous
stomach growths 7 years later,
and a significant decrease in
subsequent stomach cancer
by 15 years.
What about the garlic?
No benefit by 7 years,
and only a non-statistically
significant reduction after 15 years.
But in 2019 we got the 22-year update:
15 years after the study ended and
those who had taken the garlic did
indeed have a significantly lower risk
of subsequently dying from cancer,
though interestingly the protective
effect of garlic only seemed
to manifest among nondrinkers.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.